Preliminary Guide to the Edwin Dean Worcester Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edwin Dean Worcester papers
1881-1929
MS 563
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.75
(7 boxes)
Diaries recording principal events in Worcester's professional and personal life and trips to Europe and to England.
Worcester, Edwin D.
Scope and Contents
The Edwin Dean Worcester Papers consist mainly of Worcester's own diaries kept between 1882 and 1929. The entries mention and occasionally comment upon the principal events of each day—professional, personal, social, and familial. There are also diaries of his brother and brother-in-law, and miscellaneous papers including letters, photographs, and printed memorabilia. Three of the diaries record travel in Europe and England.
FAMILY MEMBERS MENTIONED IN DIARIES
Worcester:
Papa / Edward Dean Worcester (1828-1904)
Mamma / Mary Abigail (Low) Worcester (1830-1906)
Eddie / Edwin Dean Worcester (1856-1929; Y. 1876)
Georgie / George Henry Worcester (1857-1917)
Frankie / Franklin Eldred Worcester (1860-1891; Y. 1882)
Harry / Harry Augustus Worcester (1862-1938; Y. 1884)
Willie / Wilfred James Worcester (1864-194?; Y. 1885)
Maggie / Margaret Dows Worcester (1872-1941) (Mrs. Charles Mallory Williams)
Williams:
Charles / Charles Mallory Williams (1872-1951; Y. 1892)
Mary / Mary Low Williams (1908- ) (Mrs. Macdonald Bick)
Margery / Margaret Williams (1910- ) (Mrs. Billing B. Fairbrother)
Biographical / Historical
Edwin Dean Worcester, 1856-1929. B.A. 1876.
Born February 25, 1856, in Albany, N. Y.; died May 21, 1929, in New York City.
Father, Edwin Dean Worcester; vice-president of Lake Shore & Michigan Southern Railroad and secretary of New York Central & Hudson River Railroad; son of Eldad and Sarah (Chickering) Worcester; descendant of William Worcester, who came from England to Salisbury, Mass., about 1638. Mother, Mary (Low) Worcester; daughter of Warren S. and Mary Armenia (Walker) Low; descendant of Thomas Low, who came from England to Ipswich, Mass., about 1645. Nephew: Dean K. Worcester, '19.
Albany Boys' Academy. Third Freshman Scholarship; first and third prizes in English composition Sophomore year; philosophical oration appointment Junior year and first prize at Junior Exhibition; Salutatorian Senior year, W. W. DeForest Scholar and winner of DeForest Gold Medal; College premium in English composition; Class historian Freshman year; member Ivy Committee, Delta Kappa, Phi Theta Psi, Psi Upsilon, Skull and Bones, and Phi Beta Kappa.
LL.B. Yale 1878 (honors Senior year); clerk in law office of Hand & Hale in Albany 1878-1880; admitted to New York Bar 1879; managing clerk for Mr. Samuel Hand and also engaged in the practice of law independently 1881-1882; spent the year 1882-1883 abroad; had lived in New York City since 1883; in 1884 formed a law partnership with George C. Webb, '76 and '78 L., and Thorndike Saunders under firm name of Saunders, Webb & Worcester and continued in that connection until 1907; senior member of Worcester, Williams & Lehman 1907-1909, Worcester & Williams 1909, and Worcester, Williams & Saxe since 1909; had traveled extensively abroad; secretary of Class of 1876 since 1906 and Alumni Fund agent since 1900; foundation member of Fort Orange Club of Albany and New York Yale Club; member Association of the Bar of the City of New York, New York State Bar Association, American Bar Association, Century Association, New England Society of New York, Albany Society of New York, and Japan Society.
Unmarried.
Death due to arteriosclerosis and myocarditis. Buried in Albany Rural Cemetery. Survived by a sister, the wife of Charles M. Williams, '92 S., and two brothers, Harry A. Worcester, '84, and Wilfred J. Worcester, '85. Another brother, Franklin E. Worcester, '82 and '84 S., died in 1891.
Source: Yale University Obituary Record, 1928-1929.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Families; Law; Europe -- Description and travel; Great Britain; New York (State); Diaries; Lawyers; Worcester, Edwin D.; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory, 1881-1929
  - Diaries
    - "Diary of European Tour", 1882-1883 (Box 1)
    - 1884-1891 (Box 1)
    - 1892-1901 (Box 2)
    - 1902-1903 (Box 3)
    - "Diary of a Journey in England, taken by Will and me in August and September, 1904" (Box 3)
    - 1904-1909 (Box 3)
    - 1910-1919 (Box 4)
    - 1920-1925 (Box 5)
    - 1926-1929 May (Box 6)
  - Loose items, mostly removed from diaries
    - Manuscripts and correspondence, 1881-1926 (Box 6)
    - Photographs and postcards, 1897-1928 (Box 6)
      General
      Includes photographs of Edwin Dean Worcester, George H. Worcester, Margaret Dows Worcester, Charles Mallory Williams, Mary Low Williams, Ruth Sears Cheney, Louise Johnson, unidentified family members, and fellow-passengers on a 1911 voyage.
    - Memorabilia: stamps, calling cards, currency, tickets, 1887-1914 (Box 6)
    - Printed matter
      - Personal and miscellaneous, 1882-1926 (Box 6)
      - Clippings, 1891-1928 (Box 6)
      - Programs, 1890-1924 (Box 6)
      - Bar Association mailings, 1902-1913 (Box 6)
  - Diaries of others
    - Franklin Eldred Worcester (1860-1891), 1872-1876 (Box 7)
    - Charles Mallory Williams (1872-1951): diary of European trip, [1897?] May-August (Box 7)